# Jinal Tapar

PHYSICAL ADDRESS
Nanophotonics Lab, Academic Block C-301
Indian Institute of Technology Hyderabad
Kandi, Hyderabad INDIA 502285

ELECTRONIC ADDRESS ee17resch11009@iith.ac.in jinal.tapar18@gmail.com

### SUMMARY<sup>1</sup>

Ms. Jinal Tapar is a Ph.D. scholar working under Dr. Naresh Emani ( Google Scholar) at the department of Electrical Engineering, IIT Hyderabad and have submitted her thesis. Her research interest spans Semi-conductor Nanophotonics, Non-Hermitian systems, All-dielectric tunable metasurfaces. In her Ph.D. with Dr. Emani's group, she investigated the prospects of parity-time ( $\mathcal{PT}$ ) symmetric nanophotonic devices for light generation and manipulation bridging nanophotonics and quantum physics.

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD, Electrical Engineering	07.2017 - present
Indian Institute of Technology, Hyderabad, India	
MTech, Electronics and Communication Engineering	08.2013 - 08.2015
Amravati University, Amravati, India	
BTech, Instrumentation	07.2006 - 04.2010
Government College of Engineering, Amravati, India	

#### PROFESSIONAL CAREER

External Project Staff (INUP)	11.2016 - 04.2017
Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay	
Lecturer at ECE Dept.	07.2015 - 06.2017
HVPM College of Engineering, Amravati	

## PROFESSIONAL RECOGNITION, AWARDS AND HONOURS

Best Poster Award in Plasmonics and Photonics Symposium, IEEE ICEE 2020 conference
 University Color coat holder for best research project at state level

#### RESEARCH PROJECTS

**Thesis related:** Optical gain enhancement in semiconductor nanostructures, Effect of surface recombination on carrier lifetime, PT-symmetric metasurfaces for light generation and manipulation, Multipole analysis of gain-loss nanoantenna, dipole emission in a PT-symmetric cavity

**Collabarative:** Light generation from MIM plasmonic tunnel junctions, spatio-temporal modulation, and Mid-IR photodetection

#### TEACHING ASSISTANT EXPERIENCE

**Undergraduate courses:** Semiconductor Fundamentals, Electronic Devices and Circuits, Physics of MOS Transistors, Engineering Electromagnetics, NPTEL course - Introduction to Semiconductor Devices

**Postgraduate courses:** Introduction to Nanophotonics, VLSI Technology, and Microfabrication and Device Simulation Laboratory

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Last Updated: November 11, 2021

## PUBLICATION SUMMARY

4 refereed journal articles, 8 Conference Proceedings/talks

## SERIAL JOURNAL ARTICLES

- 5. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, and Naresh Emani, "Generalized Kerker effect in PT-symmetric nanoantenna array" (*Under review*)
- 4. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, and Naresh Emani, "Dynamically tunable asymmetric transmission in PT-symmetric phase gradient metasurface", ACS Photonics Article ASAP IF: 7.529 [doi]
- 3. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, and Naresh Emani, "Spectral singularities and asymmetric light scattering in PT-symmetric 2D nanoantenna arrays." Optics Letters 45, no. 18 (2020): 5185-5188. IF: 3.776 [doi]
- 2. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, P. Kumar, Kaushik Nayak, and Naresh Emani, "Enhancement of the optical gain in GaAs nanocylinders for nanophotonic applications." Journal of Applied Physics 127, no. 15 (2020): 153102. IF: 2.546 [doi]
- 1. Kishen, Saurabh, **J. Tapar**, and Naresh Emani, "Enhanced light emission from gap plasmons in nano-strip MIM tunnel junctions." Journal of Optics 22, no. 9 (2020): 095006. IF: 2.753 [doi]

## CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS/TALKS

- 9. **Jinal Tapar**. Non-Hermitian nanophotonics: Tailoring light with gain and loss. SPIE IITB student chapter Online Invited Lecture Series 2021. (Invited Talk)
- 8. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, Naresh Emani, "Dynamically Tunable Asymmetric Transmission in PT symmetric Metasurfaces" SPIE Active Photonic Platforms XIII, San Diego, USA, 1-5 August 2021 [link] (Oral)
- 7. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, Naresh Emani, "Spectral singularities and broadband unidirectional invisibility in 2D PT-symmetric metamaterial" META, University of Warsaw, Poland, 20-23 July 2021 [link] (Poster)
- 6. Kishen Saurabh., **J. Tapar**, Naresh Emani, "Enhanced light generation due to hybridization of lattice and gap plasmon modes in periodic MIMtunnel junction" META, University of Warsaw, Poland, 20-23 July 2021 (Poster)
- Jinal Tapar, Naresh Emani, "Exceptional scattering in PT-symmetric GaInP nanoantenna metasurfaces." Photonics and Plasmonics symposia, IEEE ICEE, IIT Delhi (virtual), 26-28 November 2020 (Best poster award) [link]
- 4. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, and Naresh Emani, "Tunable Spectral Singularities with Asymmetric Directional Response in PT-symmetric 2D Nanoantenna Array." In Frontiers in Optics, pp. FM2E-3. Optical Society of America, 2020. (Oral) [doi]
- 3. Ramya Akshita, **J. Tapar**, and Naresh Emani, "Experimental Verification of Enhanced Photoluminescence in p-doped GaAs using Fluorescence Lifetime Measurements." In 2019 Workshop on Recent Advances in Photonics (WRAP), pp. 1-3. IEEE, 2019. [doi] (Poster)
- Kishen, Saurabh, J. Tapar, and Naresh Emani. "Study of Gap Plasmons in 2D Finite Metal-Insulator-Metal Tunnel Junctions." In 2019 Workshop on Recent Advances in Photonics (WRAP), pp. 1-4. IEEE, 2019. [doi] (Poster)
- 1. **Jinal Tapar**, S. Kishen, K. Nayak, Naresh Emani, "Optimizing the Gain in Semiconductor Nanostructures for All-Dielectric Active Metamaterial Applications." ICMAT, Marina Bay Sands, Singapore, 23-28 June 2019 (Poster)